# Stéphane Vaillancourt

**IT Specialist** 



svaillancourt@gmail.com



(780) 910 - 1088



11620 9A Ave NW, 211 Edmonton, Alberta, T6J7B4



linkedin.com/in/svaillancourt1

## **About Me / Highlights of Qualifications**

IT Specialist with 8+ years of experience providing critical support to customers and internal stakeholders in a variety of operating systems, software and physical solutions.

Fully bilingual with excellent communication and de-escalation skills, passion for finding solutions across stakeholder groups and ensure customer satisfaction.

Proven leader and trainer trusted with the development of foundation operating materials for use in one–on–one and group settings.

## **Education**

# Telecommunications Engineering Technology Diploma

Northern Alberta Institute of Technology

2008 - 2010

High School Diploma

École Maurice-Lavallée

2003 - 2006

## Skills

Windows 7/8/10

Microsoft Office / Google Suites

Troubleshooting

**Project Management** 

Telephony Infrastructure (VOIP)

Microsoft SharePoint

Fiber- Optic (Splicing & Testing)

Computer Networking / IPV4

TCP/IP, UDP, VLANS, DHCP, DNS

Python, Java, SQL, HTML, CSS

**Time Management** 

**Technical Support** 

Team Leadership

VMWare/virtualization

# **Experience**

Network Technician - Consumer Test

TELUS / Edmonton, Alberta / March 2013 - July 2019

Analyzed and supported field technician with live troubleshooting, trouble reports for network services, accessing various databases and switches to ensure service information is correct and available for trouble resolution.

- Eliminated overlap/split work by creating a single point of contact for field technicians for all telephony features & Interdepartmental Patterning and Outage Support Prime, with a key focus to improve the information available to field resources and promote cooperation between internal partners
- Prepared, presented and updated training materials on various systems and procedures for
  use in individual and group settings and be the lead in training new employees in systems and
  procedures through group presentations, side-by-side shadowing, individual mentoring and
  quality assessments
- Tested and configured copper and fiber-optic telephony and Internet equipment within the network to resolve service issues
- Assessed team needs, software compatibility, added/replaced hardware and created, tested, and implemented system images. (i.e. The lead for the transition from SharePoint to Google Suits migration)
- A recipient of performance award 'Leading Stars' for being top in my workgroup for Q1 & Q2 of 2018 in tickets resolved

Service Technician (Customer Solutions Delivery)

TELUS / Edmonton, Alberta / March 2011 – February 2013

Installed, repaired, and maintained the integrity of customer premise equipment as well as outside field technology; achieved quality metrics, met industry standards and was held accountable for the quality of workmanship.

- Gained skills to install and troubleshoot hardware/service issues tied to TELUS services.
- Developed the ability to effectively handle favorable and unfavorable customer interactions
- Demonstrated the ability to engage with customers leading to and supporting residential products related to Future Friendly Home (Home Networking, ADSL High–Speed Internet, TELUS TV, etc.)
- Installed, connected and tested CAT5/CAT6, LMR, fiber-optic and other cables for both indoor and outdoor applications
- Tested fiber-optic cable using visual inspection, visual fault locator (VFL), optical loss test set (OLTS), and optical time-domain reflectometer (OTDR) devices
- Worked in close cooperation with other team members, including other technician specialists, operations support, customer service, driving process improvement, and customer satisfaction

## **Certifications**

## Computer Courses (Udemy.com)

- Python Ultimate "Zero to Hero"
- Python Automate the boring stuff
- MySQL Bootcamp: go from SQL beginner to Expert

### **Coaching Courses**

- Respect in Sport Activity Leader
- Community Coach Level 1

#### **Drivers License**

• Class 5 (Full license - Non GDL)

## Languages

- English Verbal & Written Fluent
- French Verbal & Written Fluent

# **Experience (Continued)**

## **Broadcast Technologist**

#### Canadian Broadcasting Corporation / Edmonton, Alberta / Dec 2010 - March 2011

Gathered knowledge and experience working with network connections via satellite/ISDN/direct feeds. While maintaining the server's that held the information that is being distributed to the telecommunications companies to broadcast on their networks.

- Learned skills to identify and troubleshoot hardware/service issues
- Performed installations, configuration, testing and preventative maintenance of equipment,
   systems and facilities in the Edmonton Broadcasting Center
- Experience with basic networking (TCP/IP, UDP protocols), Windows Server, radio and television broadcasting equipment
- Technical knowledge and familiarity with production and post-production methods for radio, television and new media programming
- Worked in a stressful, demanding production-centered and environment, while performing duties
  effectively under tight deadlines, producing quality work and maintained a positive, professional
  attitude

#### Junior Communications Technician

#### Glentel Inc / Edmonton, Alberta / Aug 2010 - Dec 2010

Installed, repaired and maintained the integrity of customer premise equipment as well as outside field technology; achieved quality metrics, met industry standards. I was held accountable for the quality of workmanship of the installation.

- Experience in OTDR testing, cleaning and installing fiber optic cabling
- Used sophisticated electronic test equipment, measuring devices, meters, and hand tools in analyzing, adjusting, installing, wiring, repairing, maintaining, testing wireless transmissions and associated installed equipment
- Installed, connected and tested CAT5/CAT6, LMR and other coaxial cables for both indoor and outdoor applications
- Performed required incidental and preventative maintenance on project sites, power equipment, transmission, associated equipment, completed necessary logs, reports, postings to the City of Edmonton Transit Services land mobile radio (LMR) project
- Coordinated clearing of trouble with other groups and organizations and worked with other employees and/or customers in the maintenance, installation of wireless services for the City of Edmonton Project

## References

Available upon request

## Volunteer

#### Youth Bowling Coach

Bonnie Doon Bowling Lanes / Edmonton, Alberta / October 2007 – Present

- National Coach for Alberta Boys Teams 2011, 2012, 2014, 2015, 2017 & 2019
- Webmaster for <u>Bonniedoonbowling.com</u>

#### Founder – Digital Media

Alley Hoop - Basketball Event Organization / Edmonton, Alberta / April 2015 - Present

- An Event Organization, our goal is to promote basketball events, give back to our communities by connecting with local businesses. We recently rebuilt the Blue Quill Community the community basketball courts in the Edmonton area
- Main duties include project management, graphic designer, webmaster, marketer, responsible for day to day logistical operations days of the event and prior, etc.
- Webmaster for <u>Bluequillclassic.ca</u> & <u>Provincialtournament.com</u>